[Music]
[Applause]
and over to
you okay well welcome thanks for coming
to scaling uh Obin applications so I'm
Parker and this is Shannon we've been
business partners for 15 years uh we are
obviously husband and wife this is one
of the first times we've done this with
pants on for the rehearsal so for your
benefit American pants you're welcome
most importantly we are the people
behind
Oben and I'm Shannon and when I'm not
supporting Oben customers I am cooking
world Cuisines with a myriad of spices
it's something I
love my dog our dog dog
our dog I love our
dog I dislike the bottom of swimming
pools I mean so much so that if it's
pomus I will do anything to avoid
touching it really dislike the feeling
and I'm Parker and when I'm not fixing
things in open uh usually that I broke I
love eating World Cuisine with a myriad
of spices uh maybe cleaning up I truly
love big chunky tires like you find on
track trors or construction equipment
it's like a Boyhood fantasy carried into
adulthood and I loathe backing up an
Airstream on a really crowded Street he
does it's harder harder than it looks
he's very good at it I try uh but this
talk is about scaling Obin applications
uh but we're going to start with some
things that may or may not scale very
well cargo ships cargo ships scale
incredibly well there's something that
look like they shouldn't cross an ocean
with all of our goods and yet they do
they transport and they do it
well uh trains trains scale very well
this one's overs scaled so much that
it's covered in people all along the
side my favorite is the guy at the front
making a phone
call he's got things to do and it's
working
out but not everything scales your
grandmother's knitting perhaps she
cannot knit for your customers your
clients the entire
family her poor little hands are going
to freeze up and they wanted $80 for
this on shutter stock so pardon yeah
you're getting a shutter scot
logo uh well the beam in erlang OTP is
Renown for scaling
horizontally and it's so ubiquitous that
it's reported that 50% of the world's
internet traffic goes through earling
nodes and it's uniformally used for 5G
in the US and in uh Europe
we all know that Elixir scales that's
why we're here it's been shown to scale
time and time again you may remember the
road to 2 million web stock con
connection showing the process model
scales um but slightly more obscure is
elixir RAM and the template of Doom
which demonstrates that the io model
also scales and if you've never seen
this article before it has the Stellar
endorsement of Elixir is more
interesting than any programming
language you've ever SE seen in your
life which how do you argue with that
ever
ever and as a database pogress is Renown
for versatility and its ability to scale
vertically and
horizontally as illustrated by Earth's
largest land mammals which start off
incredibly small and become Majestic
behemoths this is a postgress pond in
case you didn't catch it's an elephant
it's low fruit and I'm not above it she
let me have
it uh more practically postris has been
know to scale to 1 billion inserts a
second which is in certain optimized
situations and well beyond the reason of
what you'd need for a background job
queue and that's how we're going to talk
about this which is postgress as a queue
and we're going to be overtly technical
for a second but in the past eight years
postgress has made a lot of progress in
adding new features that make it
scalable and work as a queue starting
with in 9.4 they added Json B so you can
have a hybrid document seal relational
database very important essentially in
9.6 they added skip locked which is like
the secret sauce to being able to have
Q's at all without
contention and 12 they added reindex
concurrently which lets you rebuild your
indexes to U minimize
space and then in 13 they added B tree
duplication which is important when you
have a state machine modeled as a q
because there are a lot of duplicate
rows and it's important to be able to PR
through those quickly
and then at 14 they added optimized
skipping B splits which I don't know
what that
means you should look that up I'll make
a note of that it's good plan open is
the sum of Elixir and postgress
components that meld wonderfully and
complement each other I'm sorry to
disappoint any SQL light fans I'm not
saying you should leave the room right
now you will not self-destruct but
you're already on your path to Global
domination and we're not doing that
today so we know that combining Elixir
and postgress scales well many of us
have applications built on exactly that
stack and they work out really well the
question is whether Obin can also
scale and in the past we've shown that 1
million jobs a minute is possible in a
single queue on a single node on a mere
little laptop that's a blog post which
that is a blog post that's a blog post
with some fancy charts okay well that
showed that actually gets closer to 2
million jobs a second and that is also
possible charts are fancy charts are
data but not always proof all right we
go to the next slide we have proof so
this is an htop screenshot which shows
that four cores are heavily utilized uh
while the other six are really not doing
much and that's why the Dum row was
running so you see all those idle cores
doing nothing well you know what they
say about idle cores Parker it's a great
band name idle cores so it can scale the
small but what about the large can you
push 1 million jobs in a minute for a
whole
day which is well over 1 billion jobs a
day um yes 1.4 billion jobs yes you can
so it's a little teaser about what we're
attempting to do that we'll tell you
about later we're attempting to do that
right now while we're giving this
presentation so little live demo at the
end hopefully it all works out according
to plan Brazen huh no pressure no
pressure
well we're going to show how you can
tune cues for maximum
throughput and you can also minimize
impact on the rest of the application
these are essential qualities for
scaling minimize impact on the
database and avoid the dreaded bloat
personally I don't bloat he says that
physically this is not something that's
a problem for me yeah you say that all
the time you say you never bloat I'm a
good company where where avoiding that
that's our job to avoid the
bloat uh so we're going to talk about
some practical problems causes and
solutions things that are easily
identifiable in your own applications uh
why those are happening and then what
you can do very quickly to to address
those and we're going to start with
quick fire tips so minimize the size of
your jobs arcs um there are several
benefits to storing minimal values like
like IDs and arcs one it's less data
over the wir to the database two it's
less data stored and less data indexed
and three it's resilient to updates or
changes or if the job is retried later
which it most likely is have some
confidence I'm going
there all right so you should also prune
aggressively to get rid of old jobs so
historic jobs the ones that are
completed canceled or discarded they
just build up in the database and you
don't need to keep them around so by
letting the pruner run in the background
as a plugin it will delete those to free
up the database uh make room for
uniqueness queries and
introspection also use insert all
whenever possible this is a pretty
standard rule for application use don't
insert one thing at a time if you don't
have to uh it's just the laws of physics
if you make one insert it has to go over
the wire back and forth so bundle those
up into one insert if you can that's
fewer queries fewer
transactions each insert operation is a
round trip query to that database so
update your postrest version I think
we'll say that what two or three times
maybe more so upgrading is difficult um
I don't want to we don't want to say
that it's easy to coordinate that we all
know that it is so every postrest
version it improves performance and adds
helpful features it's worth it it looks
minimal but we know it's not but really
have you thought about upgrading your
postgress version he hars on it Obin
only supports back to version 12 and
it's currently on version 16 there are a
lot of improvements between those two
versions so you get free performance and
extra features and when we inevitably
bump that requirement you won't be left
behind so seriously consider upgrading
it's hard it's worth it
after you update scale your database the
most immediate win possible is to
vertically scale your database the
effect is instantaneous and the cost is
marginal is sure so now some realish
life scenarios this is based on feedback
that we've gotten people's emails slack
messages whatever other support channels
we've gotten and these are based on real
problems identifying the causes that
were behind them and then going through
some practical Solutions the names have
been changed to protect the innocent or
avoid direct
harassment
innocent La
Dua La asks why does our instrumentation
show PG notify at the top of our
frequent queries it's a very La question
so
la well lave does two things that are
great he asks the question and he
provides proof so we investigate clearly
that's happening oven uses Pub sub
notifications for communication between
nodes like job inserts pausing cues
resuming cues and metrics for web the
default Notifier uses postgress because
it doesn't require any extra
setup every notification requires a
separate query we tried using a single
connection a bottleneck and taint at
scale
so what do we do uh you start by rolling
back trying to use a single connection
because that doesn't work that's
actually a very bad idea uh and then
once you've done that you tell everybody
to try to use a different Notifier like
PG or process groups uh that minimizes
your load on the database uh it gets rid
of your total queries and it allows
bigger payloads it's a win all around
and if you have a functional cluster and
I mean distributed Earline cluster not
kubernetes or some other sort of cluster
then it's it's a single line change you
just go from postgress to
PG and ptis retro says inserting jobs
generates too many notifications from
the database can we disable that well
good news for pis is yes yes you can so
inserting jobs emits a trigger and the
trigger is a notification that lets any
running qes know that there's something
for them to fetch and execute and it
does this so that between the 1 second
polling time you can have a very
immediate responsive job fetch uh
originally that was part of postgress it
was done as a trigger in the database
that's the name triggers uh but that
doesn't scale very well when you do bulk
inserts because it has to D duplicate
all of those so what do we do to fix
that well managing triggers from Obin
itself provides more control and it's
made it possible to have triggers with
other notifiers like PG which is better
for
scaling a Val Val if you need a
subsecond job dispatch without it jobs
may wait up to 1 second before running
but that's not a concern for busy cues
since they're constantly fetching and
dispatching than for applications busy
that's what they're doing it's a good
thing disabling the triggers is a single
line of configuration and if you upgrade
there's a teeny tiny database migration
it's not painful at all just a teen tiny
one
milp fighten that's a real name it's the
most realistic one so far yes milp asks
how do I stop open job indexes from
taking up so much space on dis well milp
the transactional model applies to
indexes as well as tables that leaves
bloat from inserting updating and
deleting jobs and the autov vacuuming
won't always fix that
so the index situation gets better after
version 14 but they're still prone to
bloating so how do we fix that well the
bloating problem which is not a problem
for me clearly never you uh is to
reindex so use the re indexer plugin to
intermittently concurrently without any
locking or any downtime rebuild all of
those essential indexes so that does a
couple of things one it minimizes their
size on disk and it also optimizes them
to make your queries
faster um it's part of Open Source
and you can just add it to your list of
plugins normally it runs at midnight by
default but if that's a little bit too
aggressive then you can tweak it it uses
a crownlike schedule and you can have it
run weekly
instead and jevin Laxon jeevan Laxon
says inserting bulk unique jobs times
out sometimes there aren't that many
jobs what's going on it's very sassy
it's very jevic so uh well the problem
is inserting unique jobs requires an
extra query whenever it's inserted so
one query is to check for existing jobs
and the other one is an advisory lock
that ensures that different transactions
don't compete with each
other and when you stack those up
instead of making a single query to
insert a job you actually have three
queries and that doesn't scale very well
despite the fact that they're very fast
the checks just aren't free many things
aren't so
what do you
do frequently people set uniqueness for
jobs and they don't really need it this
happens a lot so first evaluate whether
or not uniqueness is necessary for your
workload reduce the work to match jobs
by selecting a single field rather than
an entire Json field it's important
avoid checking the unique period if at
all possible and if that's not possible
set the time stamp option to scheduled
at you might wonder why isn't that the
default well it just didn't exist back
then so for legacy reasons we can't
change it but now that you know you can
change it and make it all better they
can use that as an
index so as shown here it's just a few
lines of configuration in your worker
so now Shameless Pro tip and now a word
from our sponsor uh so in open Pro the
smart engine can do bulk unique inserts
in a single transaction so instead of
one query per job and one advisory lock
per job it does that in just two queries
and then it inserts them all together
fewer queries fewer
transactions wogan
wagger wogen asks how do we stop seeing
Ecto timeout errors from Obin when our
application is
busy Obin uses connections from your
applications repo pool to talk to the
database when that pool is busy it can
starve OB of connections and you're
going to see timeout errors on the other
hand despite fast queries if Oben is an
extremely busy thing at that moment it's
going to starve your application of
connections which is not what we want so
how do we fix
that well a good solution is to set up
another repo a secondary one that's
dedicated just to Oben so Obin use it to
fetch act and do the other things that
it needs to do without competing with
your applic
for those
resources so the dedicated pool isolates
those queries it's really easy to set up
as well you just pointed at the same
database little bit of configuration it
doesn't need a lot of connections Obin
actually uses very few connections by
itself most of the time uh and it's a
single line change to your config to
just point it at the other dedicated
bre so when Bilson he says pruning old
jobs works well but the size of our jobs
table is bloated and it keeps growing
again with the bloat it happens this
happens
often so problem is like
indexes the transactional system only
Flags rows for deletion later and so
when you delete it then has to flag it
and then autovacuum comes around and it
empties it but it still doesn't actually
get rid of it off the disc and the more
that you run these things the busier
that it is uh the more garbage that you
accumulate
and so you have to tune well I don't
want to give that away I'm sorry the
default settings aren't that great so
what do we
do well I mean autov vacuuming can be
tweaked for the obin's jobs table alone
just in solitary and the exact scale
factor uh it's going to
vary I feel like this is unusual because
it will be based on your unique
situation your table rows your table
size and your database load so there's
no one that's General I'm sure yeah but
it does lead to a Shameless Pro tip So
Pro tip number two which is open Pro
Dynamic partitioner instead of having to
use a pruner for deletion it partitions
all jobs and by state and then it
manages dropping those entirely and when
you drop a table there's no bloat left
over there's nothing at all it's
virtually instantaneous and another
benefit is that all of those tables are
smaller which means they have less
activity and autov vacuuming is faster
follow of those as
well ton munsky Tonica asks why do we
start to see connection errors under
Peak load in high concurrency cues well
Tonica fetching jobs takes a single
optimized query for each queue however
acing when a job finishes takes a single
connection for each job so in a busy
system with high concurrency all of the
acing causes pool contention and despite
the individual queries being very fast
this is still something that we have to
solve what do we
do well you've heard this one before um
but increase your pool size and reduce
your overal concurrency uh the ratio
between the number of jobs executing and
the number of available Connections in
your pool has to be tweaked to minimize
any competition that's
happening so start by using a dedicated
pool okay we set it before it's really
very important when you have a dedicated
pool you know a baseline of how many
connections are available for Oben
compared to your application and they
don't mix that gives you better
predictable
performance and then in extreme cases
when you're running 100 million plus
jobs a day you might want very
predictable performance and that's when
you might think about having a dedicated
database just for open jobs uh which can
help uh so here's an example a somewhat
trivial example of increasing their pool
size minimizing concurrency it's not
always that simple but just consider if
you need 50 jobs running at a time or 30
might
work and the final Pro
tip is open Pro Smart engine acts all
those jobs together so instead of a
single connection and transaction every
time a job finishes it bundles them all
together and waits and does that in a
single transaction the next time it
fetches far fewer transactions far fewer
queries all right I think it's time for
some tips so the first one isolate open
from your app it's probably the fourth
time we've said that in the last 5
minutes it is the number one quick fire
tip that we could give to you out of the
scenarios that we see most often
minimize extra transactions which is
very similar
to minimize extra queries again fewer
queries fewer transactions better off
for your
app also minimize index bloat and
minimize table
blow all right it's time to put up or
shut up
right so there's a good chance of shut
up we'll
see we get it worked earlier and this is
always what happens it works through the
run through and you decide you're just
going to go for it so so the idea is we
take all of the tips here we put them
together in a single application that
application actually runs in the
background and it should be capable of
running what is 1 billion jobs a day on
a laptop just locally while we're giving
a keynote look at this all right go
ahead and run
it oh and no you can see the
configuration but it's not happy about
it so you can try to
restart yes I'm I'm going to move it
over
H it's always the thing it's so nice to
be in a room full of friends when you
put yourself out there with a live
[Music]
demo maybe not the best idea for the
live demo I think it was a great idea oh
well uh we can always go through the
code though as well I'm trying to uh get
it off of no oh
well all right
there you
go
no yeah on
both
okay all right so there's all of the
configuration put
together which we really promise can run
700,000 jobs a minute in better
circumstances than these uh and if you
put that all together that's over 1
billion jobs a day you can see triggers
are disabled the Notifier has changed
it's partitioned it's not pruning and
it's a little bit of all of those things
put together and I can bet you if you
find us outside an hour from now he will
have this running to anyone come
there'll be a little dashboard you can
look at it it's got the things ticking
in let's
see you can try to print it again though
yeah
I can't see so
well doesn't like
it are you getting red yeah we'll
see come
on I think we're I don't know if we have
time or not we started late all right
it's disappointing all right well I'm
sorry to I'm sorry to let you down
but that's the that's the bravado of a
live demo during a talk with two people
right so we're so pleased to be here
with you it's so nice to see all of you
if you've spoken to Us online or if you
want to speak to us for the first time
we're very happy to meet you we're so
appreciative of our people and The
Elixir community and we're so proud to
be here thank you for your time AB
I
[Music]
[Applause]